The top of today's דף daf is צדי ו Tzadi Vav 96.
We are a little behind, we pick up on the top third
of צדי ה עמוד ב Tzadi He Amud Bet by the צדדין
tzidim where the two dots. We're dealing with a ברייתא Baraita that
had three opinions about how to deal with the case of somebody
who steals a פרה parah that's pregnant and it gives birth, or
a רחל Rachel that has wool and shears it. And the first
position was רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that you have to give back
both the shorn sheep and the פרה parah that had given birth
together with the גיזות gizot and with the ולדות. veladot. And the
גמרא Gemara says that even though he holds שינוי קונה Shinuy Koneh
and you really should own the shearings and pay the difference, but
this was a קנס. kenas. You shouldn't be profiting off of somebody
else's stolen, off of an object that you stole from someone else.
Now the גמרא Gemara turns to the positions of רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Let's take a look. It's about
ten lines from the top on צדי ה עמוד ב. Tzadi He
Amud Bet. רבי יהודה אומר גזילה חוזרת בעיניה. Rabbi Yehuda omer gezelah
chozeret be'einya. The גזילה gezelah goes back in its current state, which
could mean you give back the shorn sheep and the פרה parah
that had given birth and you don't pay the difference. But the
גמרא Gemara understands what this means is that you actually give it
back in the way that you took it, so you do pay
the difference. רבי שמעון אומר רואין אותה כאילו היא שומה אצלו בכסף.
Rabbi Shimon omer ro'in otah ke'ilu hi shumah etzlo bekesef. You assess
the value of it, which also means you determine how much it
was when you stole it and that's what you pay. So those
both seem to be very similar positions. By the way, neither of
them are clear whether you own the גיזות. gizot. Is the fact
that the sheep has been sheared enough of a שינוי Shinuy in
the sheep itself? That remains pretty vague here. But anyway, the גמרא
Gemara understands that either way they're both saying you pay for the
value when you stole it. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו?
Mai beinayhu? So what's the difference between these two positions? אמר
זביד בשבח שעל גבי גזילה קמיפלגי. Amar Zevid beshevach she'al gabi gezelah
kamiflagi. Okay, the question is about the improvement. Let's say you had
not sheared it. So who gets that improved value?
רבי יהודה סבר דנגזל הוי. Rabbi Yehuda savar denigzal havei. ורבי שמעון
סבר דגזלן הוי. veRabbi Shimon savar degazlan havei. So רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is of the position that it belongs to the נגזל, nigzal,
the person who it was stolen from. Let me just check רש״י
Rashi very quickly, make sure I'm saying this right.
רש״י Rashi said yesterday that it was השתא hashtah according to רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. השתא. hashtah. He said כמות שהיא עכשיו. kemot shehi
achshav. What? רש״י Rashi said yesterday that בעיניה be'einya means כמות שהיא
עכשיו. kemot shehi achshav. כמות שהיא עכשיו, kemot shehi achshav, ready,
he returns it, וחוזר ומשלם דמי גיזות וולדות. vechozer umeshalem dmei gizot
uveladot. Yeah, but you pay the difference. Okay,
so anyway, the גמרא Gemara says the difference could be that you
haven't sheared it yet. Okay.
So אמר זביד בשבח שעל גבי גזילה קמיפלגי רבי יהודה סבר דנגזל
הוי. Amar Zevid beshevach she'al gabi gezelah kamiflagi Rabbi Yehuda savar denigzal
havei. That belongs to the נגזל. nigzal. So when he says חוזרת
בעיניה, chozeret be'einya, it means that had you not yet sheared it,
you would have given it back with the increased wool. Let's say
it had grown wool since you stole it. That would belong to
the נגזל. nigzal. ורבי שמעון סבר דגזלן הוי. veRabbi Shimon savar degazlan
havei. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, the גזלן gazlan would
get that. So that's an interesting idea that even some type of
a, you know, small increase in its value, in the wool, in
the whatever, that would be yours. What is that? Is that based
on שינוי? Shinuy? Why would the גזלן gazlan get it? Like that
seems to be a small enough change, an incremental enough change, and
that's pretty strange that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say that belongs
to the גזלן. gazlan. But the emphasis of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that says חוזרת בעיניה chozeret be'einya is being read here to mean
not in the specific scenario discussed in the ברייתא, Baraita, but if
there was a small increase, you know, growth in the wool, let's
say, that would go back with the increase to the owner. That's
what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say.
So are we talking about the ברייתא, Baraita, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
or רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon are not?
Well, they're both saying the same thing but their positions indicate that
there would be a different area that they would be debating. In
the case of the ברייתא, Baraita, they're saying you pay what it
was when it was stolen. But the different language indicates that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say that in some cases you'd give it
back even though it had improved and you would not just pay
the value when you stole it. רב פפא אמר דכולי עלמא שבח
שעל גבי גזילה דגזלן הוי. Rav Pappa amar dechulei alma shevach she'al
gabi gezelah degazlan havei.
Which is again a shocker. Like, you know, why is this small
little increase, I mean, what does that base then? Is that based
on שינוי קונה? Shinuy Koneh? Why does he get the fact that
now, you know, it's grown some extra wool? Why does that go
to the גזלן? gazlan? So תוספות, Tosafot, and you see there's a
long תוספות, Tosafot, and תוספות Tosafot basically says that these positions that
the גזלן gazlan gets to keep it is really a type of
a תקנת השבים. Takkanat HaShavim. It doesn't make sense. It's not a
שינוי קונה. Shinuy Koneh. I have it, it has this much wool,
it grows a little extra wool, all of a sudden that's a
שינוי Shinuy and I get the additional wool? So תוספות Tosafot says
no, no, no. That's because to make it easier for you to
return the קרן, keren, we let you keep the שבח. shevach. Okay.
But the principal could be very different. If it was, no, that's
true.
There are certain degrees. But to say it in a categorical way
that you get to keep the שבח shevach doesn't seem to be
a good basis for it. So תוספות Tosafot says now that the
גמרא's Gemara saying they both would hold that, that's basically a תקנת
השבים. Takkanat HaShavim. So if that's true, so both of them are
agreeing you pay for it the way it was when it was
stolen. If it increases, you the גזלן gazlan keeps the difference. Again,
תקנת השבים. Takkanat HaShavim. If it gives birth, then you pay for
it as it was worth when it was stolen. They both agree
basically you're paying what it was worth when it was stolen. So
what's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara says, דכולי עלמא שבח גבי
דגזלן הוי והכא למחצה לשליש ולרביע קמיפלגי. de-khulei alma shevach gabei de-Gazlan
havei ve-hakha le-makhtze le-shlish u-le-revia kamiflegi.
Here the question is whether you basically keep all of the increase
or do you keep a portion of it. Because we figure like
half a third that would be the amount you would pay like
a I guess it was land you'd call it a sharecropper I
don't know what you would call it anyway but you would pay
somebody who was going to raise your
sheep or raise your cows and get them pregnant and have kids
or whatever you give them a percentage of the business. So this
is like this is not a minimum payment for your services this
is like what you would contract somebody at. So everybody agrees like
what are we going to give the גזלן Gazlan so he feels
it's so funny to incentivize him to return the thing so he
feels he's at least getting something for his efforts that he now
got this cow or this sheep to be worth more. Do you
let him keep all the שבח Shevach or do you let him
keep a portion of the שבח? Shevach? Okay and that's the debate.
That makes sense what the debate is beginning to anyway, they just
had more wool it was doing in doing... I understand.
Well you grazed it you cared for it I mean you gotta
take care of it. והכא למחצה לשליש ורביע קמיפלגי. ve-hakha le-makhtze le-shlish
u-revia kamiflegi. רבי יהודה סבר שבח שעל גבי גזילה כולי דגזלן הוי.
Rabbi Yehuda savar shevach she-al gabei gezeila kulei de-Gazlan havei It's all
the גזלן Gazlan and that's the phrase חוזרת בעיניה. chozeres be-eineha. You
give it back and Michael this is sort of the way you
wanted to say it. You give it back in exactly the way
it was when you stole it and you keep all of the
increase. Okay that's חוזרת בעיניה. chozeres be-eineha. You keep all of the
increase. Now that doesn't mean that you pay back less than it
was worth, okay, you pay it back as it was when it
was taken and so if now you shore it and it's less
than it is you have to make up the difference but any
more than that any increase from the way it was when it's
taken is all yours. ורבי שמעון סבר ve-Rabbi Shimon savar now Rabbi
Shimon uses the phrase ישמנו אותו yeshamnu oso you assess its value.
No did I skip a line? No no.
ורבי שמעון סבר
ve-Rabbi Shimon savar למחצה לשליש ורביע הוא דשקיל גזלן. le-makhtze le-shlish u-revia
hu de-shakil Gazlan.
So when he uses the phrase and says יראוה כאילו היא שומה
yera'uha ke-ilu hi shuma you assess it so assess means okay doesn't
mean the full amount you assess the value and you do
some function of that amount. So therefore everybody agrees that you pay
it back as it was when it was stolen if you shore
it you pay the difference if you haven't shorn it and it's
still שבח Shevach that's on it so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
you keep the entire increase and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you
keep a portion of the entire increase. Yes Charlie.
So I have a pregnant cow. Yes thank you. It gives birth
I give
back no okay
I give back the now non-pregnant cow.
What about the calf?
You keep it because שינוי קונה. shinui koneh.
But it was part of the
the calf was part of the cow.
So you pay the difference that's what I've been saying you everybody
agrees you pay minimum you pay the full amount of it was
when it was worth and the question is do you keep and
if it gave birth or you shore it everybody agrees you keep
that that's שינוי קונה shinui koneh and if you have to pay
the difference you'll pay the difference but otherwise you pay whatever you
know but if it just increased and without giving
birth so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you keep not you keep
you're not going to shear it but you get paid for the
full amount of increase and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you get
paid for a portion of the increase. Okay it's so crazy how
nice we're being to the גזלן Gazlan here not enough that the
תורה Torah says there's no fine but he actually he has to
get now paid for his efforts. רבי יהודה סבר Rabbi Yehuda savar
שבח שעל גבי גזילה כולי דגזלן הוי shevach she-al gabei gezeila kulei
de-Gazlan havei. oh we did that. Okay. תנן Tnan גזל פרה ונתעברה
אצלו וילדה gazal para ve-nis-abra etzlo ve-yalda רחל ונטענה אצלו וגזזה rachel
ve-nit-ana etzlo ve-gezaza so this is our משנה Mishnah fine getting back
to that. רחל ונטענה אצלו וגזזה. rachel ve-nit-ana etzlo ve-gezaza.
So you stole a cow became pregnant gave birth so went through
the full cycle or a sheep that it got laden with wool
and it was shorn. Okay משלם כשעת הגזילה. meshalem kish-as ha-gezeila.
You pay back like it was when you stole and you keep
the whole increase because now it's back to the way it was
when you stole it. So גמרא Gemara says ילדה אין לא ילדה
לא הדרא בעיניה. yalda in lo yalda lo hadra be-eineha.
It sounds like only because it gave birth do you return it
now
only because it gave birth now do you return it as it
was when it was stolen right so now you're giving back the
same thing that you stole a cow that's not pregnant. Let's say
it hadn't given birth what's the implication of the משנה? Mishnah? You
stole the cow and it got pregnant you stole the sheep and
it got laden with wool. The implication of the משנה Mishnah would
be give the whole thing back right it sounds like only because
you shore it and maybe there's a שינוי shinui on the wool
do you keep the wool but had you not done that it
sounds like the whole thing goes back okay so that's not like
we've been saying. So גמרא Gemara says בשלמא לרב זביד דאמר שבח
שעל גבי גזילה דנגזל הוי לרבי יהודה bishlama le-Rav Zevid de-amar shevach
she-al gabei gezeila de-nigzal havei le-Rabbi Yehuda
according to רב זביד Rav Zevid that was the debate of רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon whether when it increased
before it was shorn does it all belong to the נגזל nigzal
or all belong to the גזלן. Gazlan. So according to that version
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said it all belongs to the נגזל
nigzal הני רבי יהודה היא hani Rabbi Yehuda hi that's רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. אלא לרב פפא ela le-Rav Papa
the second version דאמר דגזלן הוי de-amar de-Gazlan havei
everybody says it's the גזלן's Gazlan and the question is just all
of it or part of it? הא מני? ha mani? Who is
this going like? The implication that had it not... it had been
shorn, it developed the wool when you had stolen it, it hadn't
been shorn, the implication of the משנה Mishna is that it all
goes back. So who's that going like? לא רבי יהודה ולא רבי
שמעון, Lo Rabbi Yehuda v'lo Rabbi Shimon, not רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
not רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אמר לך רב פפא, Amar lach Rav
Papa, רב פפא Rav Papa will say to you, הוא הדין אפילו
לא ילדה נמי כשעת גזילה. Hu hadin afilu lo yalda nami kishas
g'zeila.
Really when the משנה Mishna says it goes back to the נגזל,
Nigzal, that would be true even had it not yet given birth
and you didn't need שינוי טונה. Shinui Toneh. Okay, נמי כשעת
גזילה הוא דמשלם. nami kishas g'zeila hu d'meshalem. והא דקתני, V'ha d'ktani,
I'm sorry, did I say that wrong?
אפילו לא ילדה, Afilu lo yalda, even had it not yet given
birth, you would have kept the increase. Okay, you would not have
given it back. So the same way when it gives birth, you
keep the baby in the משנה, Mishna, had it not given birth,
you always would also have kept the increase and you would have
only given it back based on the value when you stole it.
Okay, נמי כשעת גזילה הוא דמשלם. nami kishas g'zeila hu d'meshalem. והא
דקתני ילדה, V'ha d'ktani yalda, so why does the משנה Mishna say
when it gave birth you get to keep the calf, which implies
before it gave birth you did not get to keep the
increase? איידי דנסיב רישא ילדה נסיב סיפא נמי ילדה. Aidi d'nasiv reisha
yalda nasiv seifa nami yalda. The רישא reisha was talking about ילדה,
yalda, remember the רישא reisha said you stole a pregnant cow and
it gave birth. So the סיפא seifa was also talking about ילדה
yalda when you stole a cow that wasn't pregnant. But the real
point is that in the משנה, Mishna, you always keep the increase,
whether you stole it not pregnant and it had now, you know,
gotten pregnant, whether you stole pregnant and it gave birth, or whether
you stole not pregnant, got pregnant, gave birth, you always pay because
that's actually the end line of the משנה. Mishna. You know the
funny thing with this is pointing out is that the משנה Mishna
is missing this obvious case. Right, the משנה Mishna says if you
took a stolen cow a pregnant cow and it gave birth, you're
משלם כשעת גזילה, meshalem kishas g'zeila, you keep the baby. You stole
a non-pregnant cow got pregnant and it gave birth, you keep the
baby, you're משלם כשעת גזילה. meshalem kishas g'zeila. This is the rule,
you're משלם כשעת גזילה, meshalem kishas g'zeila, you're משלם meshalem like it
was when it was stolen. But it didn't tell you the missing
case, the case of when you stole it not pregnant and it
got pregnant and now it's pregnant. Do you have to, do you
get to keep the increase or do you whatever? So what this
is coming down is this is coming down on the side of
זה הדין לעולם משלם כשעת גזילה. zeh hadin l'olam meshalem kishas g'zeila.
So even in that missing case where it wasn't pregnant then got
pregnant, you get to get paid back for the increase and you
only have to pay the owner for that original value. Okay, so
that's the principle of משלם כשעת גזילה. meshalem kishas g'zeila. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אתניא כוותיה דרב פפא, Atani k'vasi
d'Rav Papa, we taught like רב פפא Rav Papa that everybody agrees
the גזלן Gazlan keeps the increase and the only question is to
what degree. רבי שמעון אומר רואין אותה כאילו היא שומה אצלו בכסף
ולמחצה ולשליש ולרביע. Rabbi Shimon omer ro'in osa k'ilu hi shuma etzlo
b'kesef v'lemechtza v'lishlish v'lirvia. At least clarifies רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position,
not רבי יהודה's. Rabbi Yehuda רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you get
to keep a portion of the increase, presumably whether it's a half,
a third, or a quarter has to do with whatever the standards
are in that locale. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, so רב
אשי Rav Ashi says: כי הוינא בי רב כהנא, Ki aveina bei
Rav Kahana, when I was in the house of רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana, איבעיא לן, iba'iya lan, we asked the following question: רבי שמעון
דאמר למחצה ולשליש ולרביע הוא דשקיל, Rabbi Shimon d'amar lemechtza v'lishlish v'lirvia
hu d'shakil, גזלן כי מסלקינן ליה בדמי מסלקינן ליה או דלמא מדישרא
שקיל? Gazlan ki mesalkinan lei b'damim mesalkinan lei o dilma middishra shakil?
So until now we've even been saying you pay for the מדישרא,
middishra, right? He's not going to say like I'm going to come
and I'm going to shear off, you know, my portion of the
wool, or what are you going to do about the pregnant cow,
I'm going to come and I'm going to take a piece of
it, but here the question is maybe not. Are you allowed, do
you allowed to, I mean it's just again so disturbing and shocking
the way the גזלן Gazlan has rights here. Are you allowed to
pay him off for his portion, or does he have rights and
he says no, I own ten percent of the cow, I own,
right, I own fifty percent
of the עובר, Ubar, and when it gets of the fetus and
when it gets born that calf is going to be half mine?
Right, it's like the mafia, it's like okay right we're partners now,
you want your cow back? Fine, now we're partners in your cow.
Anyway, okay so
or do you get to at least just pay him for his
efforts? Okay ופשטינה מהא, u'pashkinah meiha,
we concluded from the following statement: אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל שלשה
שמין להן השבח ומסלקינן להו בדמי. Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel shelosha
shamin lahen hashvach v'mesalkinan lehu b'damim. Three people you assess the increase
and pay them off and they don't remain partners. Okay, now the
point here is that we're going to assume this is like it,
we're going to assume that שלשה shelosha is not a דווקא, davka,
we're going to assume the fact that he's giving you this example
of people that you get to pay off that the גזלן Gazlan
would also obviously fall into this category. Okay and these are they:
בכור לפשוט. Bechor l'pashut. Let's say two brothers inherit an estate and
because the בכור Bechor gets פי שנים, pi shnayim, right? If there's
just two brothers for simplicity, he gets two-thirds and the other brother
gets a third. Now let's say the brother goes, the בכור Bechor
goes and he plants the field and increases it and now it's
worth a thousand dollars more than it was before. דהלכה Dehalacha is
that he does not get two-thirds of that thousand dollars. Since that
was an increase in the value that occurred after you know the
inheritance took place, they split that increase equally. Okay, so because the
estate has yet to be divided. So that's an increase in the
estate, it's not like your third increased X 330 and my third
increased 660, it's that the entire estate increased. How do we divide
this new part of the estate? Well, we divide it equally. Okay,
so in that case Okay, but the point what we're going to
do is we're going to divide the land two thirds and one
third. So now I'm the בכור, Bechor, I've got more of the
increase because we divide the land two thirds and one third and
the increase was equally distributed, I've got more of the increase than
I'm entitled to. Okay, so Charlie do you get to demand a
percentage of this land? No, I'm entitled to pay you off and
keep my two thirds of lands with the full amount of increase
and pay you for that for that extra amount that I took.
Okay so that's the בכור לפשוט Bechor le'pashut ובעל
חוב דלוקח
u'ba'al chov
de'lo'ke'ach and a debtor for the for the purchaser. So the case
is is that let me just double check רש״י Rashi here again.
Right, so this was again, this was Michael owed me a thousand
dollars, he went and he sold the field to Charlie, Charlie increased
the value of the field five hundred dollars, I am now going
to come and seize that property because actually Michael owed me fifteen
hundred, whatever, Michael owed me fifteen hundred dollars or whatever it was.
I'm going to seize the entire property with the increase. Okay, but
Michael says but you don't have right to take from me more
than, I mean we're going to explore this in a minute, but
you don't have a right to take from me sort of like
more than my purchase price. I mean, your lien on that land
was only a thousand dollars, that increase five hundred that was my
input into that land, you don't have rights to that. Okay but
I'm not going to take less of the whole plot of land,
I'm going to take the whole plot of land. So Charlie now
though is entitled to five hundred dollars back, that was what he
put into the land, that wasn't the original stuff I had a
lien on. So he, so there I can pay him the five
hundred dollars rather than have him remain a partner in the land.
That's בעל חוב לוקח. Ba'al chov loke'ach. One minute. בעל
חוב לוקח Ba'al chov loke'ach ובעל חוב דיתמי u'ba'al chov de'yasmi which
is exactly the same thing, except rather than the fact that the
creditor sold the land, the creditor died and I'm taking it from
the orphans and they've increased the value, so what they've added to
the land is not what I have my liens on. So when
I am taking the land, I have to pay them for their
part, but they're not allowed to, I have the right to do
that. They're not allowed to say we're not taking your money, we're
remaining partners in the land. Okay, so the same way all of
that is true and they're all very similar cases, something that is
mine that somebody else increased, okay, and something that's mine that somebody
else increased, that person though is, I'm allowed to get rid of
that person by paying them off. Okay, so in this case also,
the גזלן gazlan increased it, רב שמעון Rav Shimon says he has
a certain he gets some money out of that, but I'm allowed
to pay him off. Okay, he's not he can't insist that he
remains a partner in it. Yes, wait Charlie had his hand up.
Just a quickie, in any sense
significance fact they're using the word בדמים bidamim rather than בכסף? bekessef?
דמים Damim is Aramaic, כסף kessef is like Mishnaic language, so I
think it's just because it's like you know it's Aramaic.
So it's not really like not pieces of or something then because
it's like somebody who made money for you and you're giving them
a commission.
Exactly, exactly. Now I never asked them to do this for me
or whatever, but right, exactly. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, okay so presumably that's the case. Now the גמרא Gemara
says אמר ליה רב פפא לרב אשי amar lei Rav Papa le'Rav
Ashi מי אמר שמואל בעל חוב לוקח יהיב ליה שבח? mi amar
Shmuel Ba'al chov loke'ach ya'hiv lei shevach?
Is that really true in this case? Yeah when I'm going now
collecting from Charlie and I had a thousand, it was worth a
thousand dollars I had a lien on the property and now I
have to pay Charlie for his for the amount that he said
he increased the value? והאמר שמואל בעל חוב גובה את השבח? ve'ha'amar
Shmuel Ba'al chov goveh es ha'shevach? That the בעל חוב ba'al chov
gets to collect the increased value. If that debt was fifteen hundred
dollars, thank you very much Charlie for increasing the value of the
land, I had a lien on that land and now I'm going
to take the whole thing, I don't owe you anything. Okay by
the way there's a middle position which is not that I don't
owe you anything or that I get to take it all, but
I pay you for your efforts, right? You know, there's a middle
position there. But anyway, here you have these contradictory statements. One of
שמואל Shmuel says that I have to reimburse Charlie for the increase
that he made in the land and the other is is that
I get to take the whole thing. אמר ליה לא קשיא כאן
בשבח המגיע לכתפים כאן בשבח שאינו מגיע לכתפים. amar lei lo kashya
kan be'shevach ha'magiya li'ktefayim kan be'shevach she'eino magiya li'ktefayim. Has the increase
reached your shoulders or not? Now what does that mean? So רש״י
Rashi says מגיע לכתפים magiya li'ktefayim means like the wheat is very
high and it's ready to be harvested. So if the wheat is
ready to be harvested, then it's really not seen conceptually as part
of the land anymore, then I'm really just taking something which conceptually
is now Charlie's wheat. Imagine he had already harvested it. Certainly I
wouldn't have a right to take it with my lien. So therefore
even while it's still attached to the land, I have to pay
him back for it. If it's not yet ready to be harvested,
then it's seen as just increase of the land itself value of
the land itself and I am entitled to take it. Okay so
now again that's pretty funny, do I not have to pay Charlie
for his efforts? But anyway but fundamentally that's just seen as a
greater value of the land, not something distinct from the land and
I am entitled to take it. Okay so then the גמרא Gemara
says ומעשה בכל יום דקמגבי שמואל אפילו שבח המגיע לכתפים. u'ma'aseh be'chol
yom de'ka'magvi Shmuel afilu shevach ha'magiya li'ktefayim.
One minute you can't say that because we know that in practice
שמואל Shmuel allows the collection of a lien even if it increased.
increases, and even if now the wheat is at standing at shoulder
height. Now that's very strange. תוספות Tosafot doesn't like that idea, says,
"Really? How could that be that the wheat is ready to be
harvested and you still have a right to it in terms of
your lien?" So תוספות Tosafot explains שבח המגיע לכתפיים shevach hamagia l'ktafai
in a different way. He says that it basically means something that
happened—he says it's sort of like did you have to put in
a lot of like, you know, backbreaking labor in order to make
it.
שבח שאינו מגיע לכתפיים shevach she'eino magiya l'ktafai means it didn't—it grew
by itself, like what Michael talked about before. You had an orchard
and it just rained. That's not מגיע לכתפיים. magiya l'ktafai. That was
like a natural increase. So for example out of hand, Charlie didn't
put in any effort, you know, the fruits just blossomed over the
course of the year, it rained and the fruits blossomed. I'm not
giving him anything for what it increased in its value. That was
land I had a lien on which natural growth and I'm taking
it all. שבח המגיע לכתפיים shevach hamagia l'ktafai means the שבח shevach
came about because of effort and labor, and that, Charlie should be
entitled to get paid back. And then the גמרא Gemara says, "One
minute, but we know that שמואל Shmuel allowed you to collect even
when it required the labor of the person. So how does that
make sense?" אמר ליה לא קשיא, amar lei lo kashya, that's not
difficult. הא דמסיק ביה כשיעור ארעא ושבחא הא דלא מסיק ביה אלא
כשיעור ארעא. ha d'masik bei k'shiur ara v'shvacha ha d'lo masik bei
ela k'shiur ara. The question is, how big was my—how big was
the loan? If Michael owes me $1,500 and the land was a
thousand, then even though now because of Charlie's effort it increased to
500, I'm entitled to seize the whole thing. Okay, now,
so
now but however if the loan was only a thousand, then I'm—see
I'm not entitled. Which basically means, okay, obviously if the loan was
only a thousand I'm not entitled to take more than the loan.
So that resolution,
right, excuse me,
where the only time I have to pay back Charlie is if
I'm really not—if my loan isn't that big. But if the loan
is that big, even though the lien was only a thousand, even
though the land started as a thousand, but because I have an
outstanding loan of 1,500 and now the land has increased, even though
it increased because of Charlie's effort, still that's my land, it's the
land I have a lien on, now it's worth the full value
of the loan, I'm entitled to take it all. It does seem
very unfair, like where's Charlie getting reimbursed for his effort? At least
I should have to—if not give him all the שבח, shevach, at
least give him something. Well let's just get to the end of
this and then I'll take the questions. Okay. אמר ליה הניחא למן
דאמר אי אית ליה זוזי לוקח לא מצי מסלק ליה לבעל חוב
שפיר. amar lei ha nicha l'man d'amar i it lei zuzai lokach
lo matzi misalak lei l'baal chov shapir. This idea that, you know,
that what do you call it, that I get to pay Charlie
off in the case when I have to do that,
when it's what do you call it when the loan was only
a thousand, so now I'm taking the whole piece of land and
I'm paying him the difference. That makes sense if according to the
one that says that if the purchaser has money he cannot make
me go away, meaning for—let's say I come, forget whether Charlie increased
it or not. I've got a lien on the land, I'm going
to seize the land that Charlie bought off of Michael, but Charlie
says, "Look, I really don't want to lose this land. Just take
this thousand dollars." Meaning Michael has to reimburse me anyway, he gave
me the insurance or whatever, take the value, don't take the land.
Is he entitled to do that? Or can I say, "I'm sorry.
You don't owe me a thousand dollars, I have rights to the
land, I'm taking the land, you don't have a right to make
me go away just by giving me the money." That's a debate.
So the גמרא Gemara says, let's see how that plays out.
Didn't we just have the פסידא psida versus the זוזי zuzi before?
That's the opposite, that's if I can pay him off for his
part. Here's whether he has a right to make me go away.
Okay, so that's the question. So let's take a look. הניחא למן
דאמר, ha nicha l'man d'amar, according to the one that says it's
good, אי אית ליה זוזי לוקח, i it lei zuzai lokach, if
Charlie has the money, לא מצי מסלק ליה לבעל חוב, lo matzi
misalak lei l'baal chov, he can't make me go away, שפיר, shapir,
then it makes sense. Because then this is the flip side of
it. I can take the whole land and pay him money, and
he can't stop me from doing that, because anyway—because he wouldn't have
a right to make me go away even if he had money.
That makes sense. אלא למן דאמר אי אית ליה זוזי לוקח מצי
מסלק ליה לבעל חוב, ela l'man d'amar i it lei zuzai lokach
matzi misalak lei l'baal chov, if Charlie had money he could make
me go away, so now think about it: if Charlie had the
money, he could make me go away from the whole land. Now
I'm taking the land, and he wants to at least keep his
$500 worth of it. It should seem that he should be entitled,
since he in general has—could be able to make me go away
had he had the means to do that, right? So why do
I get to take the 500 and pay him the money even
if he wants to keep that 500? So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא למן דאמר אי אית ליה זוזי לוקח מצי מסלק ליה לבעל
חוב, ela l'man d'amar i it lei zuzai lokach matzi misalak lei
l'baal chov, לימא
ליה, leima lei, Charlie should say to me, אי הוה לי זוזי,
i hava li zuzai, if I had cash on hand, הוה מסלקינא
לך מכולי ארעא, hava mesalkina lach mikulei ara, I'd make you go
away from the whole land, I'd give you your thousand dollars and
I'd keep everything. השתא, hashta, now that I don't have money and
you took the whole land which is worth 1,500, since fundamentally I
should be able to make you go away—make you go away, I
have some real rights here. הבו לי גריווא דארעא שיעור שבחאי, havu
li griva d'ara shiur shevachai, at least leave me a plot of
land worth my $500. Okay, so it should seem that he should
be entitled to do that, okay, since he has a $500 rights
to the land and since he has a right. right to make
me go away if he had cash, it would seem that that's
the combination of those two means that he could keep his piece,
a piece of the land worth his value.
אמר ליה, Amar lay, הכא במאי עסקינן Hacha b'mai iskinan דשיויה ניהליה
אפותיקי. d'shavivah nihaleh apotiki. The case is that Michael here who was
the one who owed me money made this plot of land be
אפותיקי. apotiki. אפותיקי apotiki means it is the only, it is the
designated collateral. It's not just I have general liens on all Michael's
property, I have focused liens on this plot of land. And what
that does is on the one hand it weakens my rights to
any other property that Michael has, but it strengthens my rights to
this plot of land. And because of that, Charlie doesn't have any
rights. He can't make me go away if he had money. Okay?
So in that case, דאמר ליה לא יהא לך פרעון אלא מזו,
d'amar lay lo yeheh lacha piraon ella mizo, I can only collect
from this. So that's the case where I can make Charlie go
away rather than him making me go away, okay, in the special
case of an אפותיקי. apotiki. But anyway, the more interesting question here
is basically this is all a digression of the case about when
the גזלן gazlan increases the value, can I pay the גזלן gazlan
and make him go away? And the answer basically was yes. And
similarly if a לקוח lokeach increases the value of property I have
a lien on, I seize the property and I make him go
away. But the גמרא Gemara said that's not so clear because it
actually might be that he could make me go away or at
least he could be entitled to keeping the amount that he has
rights to. But the strange thing is the issue about when according
to this that when even if he increases the value, if that's
equal to the value of my loan, I'm able to seize the
whole thing, okay, and presumably not even have to pay him anything,
which is very strange because one would imagine I'd at least have
to pay him for his effort. Yes Michael, you had a question.
According to the ראשונים Rishonim it says מחצה
שליש ורביע. mechetza shlish u'rvia. So let's say a shepherd sees like
you know, the sheep got really sick and I went to the
vet. And like you know, and then he put in there was
more than you know, if he capped the value of the sheep
or do you say like listen you know,
one more time, what he put in one more time, מחצה שליש
ורביע? mechetza shlish u'rvia?
I guess you know, he gets compensated like taking care of it,
let's say it's something extraordinary, take it to the vet and that's
a big vet bill. Right. So then does he get compensated for
that or do you say listen I know, your vet bill's a
thousand dollars, the sheep's only worth fifty.
No, מחצה שליש ורביע mechetza shlish u'rvia is not a portion of
what he paid, it's a percentage of the increase.
I don't have to pay for the גזלן, gazlan, if the גזלן
gazlan spent money and lost money on it, I don't have to
reimburse him, okay? He only gets a portion of the increase. Okay?
Right, but also I thought that he gets compensated as if he
was like you know, shepherd taking care of it during that time,
whatever.
No, that's the מחצה שליש ורביע mechetza shlish u'rvia because that would
normally be the arrangement but it would be a percentage of the
increase in value, it would not be a flat fee.
Okay, how do they know it's מחצה שליש ורביע? mechetza shlish u'rvia?
It depends on what the normal, what the going rate was.
So if he took it to the
vet then he doesn't get compensated for that at all? Correct. Now
there is a גמרא Gemara that talks about in other scenarios of
ירד לתוך שדה חבירו yarad l'toch s'deh chaveiro that you're
משלם m'shalem him, like you know according to the הוצאה, hotza'ah, according
to his cost. But there it's only says only if it's less
than the שבח. shevach. If it's between the הוצאה hotza'ah and the
שבח, shevach, you pay the lesser of the two. By the way,
תוספות Tosafot points out that one of the reasons behind why I
might be able to take the entire amount from Charlie and not
have to pay him for his cost is because Michael
has insured Charlie against loss. So I might as well take, think
what's gonna happen, I'm gonna take it from Charlie. Charlie now has
lost land worth sixteen hundred dollars, five hundred of which was stuff
that he inputted on his own, but it's not unfair to Charlie
because he's just gonna go back to Michael and Michael's gonna owe
him fifteen hundred dollars. Before Michael owed me fifteen hundred dollars, now
he owes Charlie fifteen hundred dollars. So one of the ways to
understand why I'm entitled to do that is because Charlie's insured against
loss. Okay, but then תוספות Tosafot explores the cases about what if
Charlie isn't insured against loss, am I still entitled to do that?
Alright, but at least that helps explain a little bit about why
that works. Okay, let's now continue in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, גזל
והשביח ומכר. gazal v'hishbiach u'machar. This has gotta be, I gotta tell
you, it's almost like Twilight Zone we're talking here about like yesterday
or two days ago we were Twilight Zone that the גזלן gazlan
tries to return and you don't accept it. No, no, no, we're
not accepting it, especially if you're a professional גזלן, gazlan, you don't
have to pay back anything. Okay?
By the way, as a matter of fact, you know a great
example of a case about somebody who's like, it was a case
of like you know stealing from like everybody and then having to
figure out how you pay back. Do people know the story about
Crazy Eddie's? You know about the guy, they were these, I think
it was Syrians or something whatever it was, they had these electronics
stores. Anyway, they had like, it was insane. I remember their ads.
Anyway, there was like all these scams going on, I don't remember
the story about it, and they were finally caught and put in
jail. Anyway, one of the guys really felt like tremendous remorse and
he's like spent the last twenty years trying to basically figure out
how to pay back the public, you know, so he goes around
and he lectures about it and whatever, you know, so it's like
anyway, but here you so we had one Twilight Zone which was
like oh you're a professional גזלן, gazlan, we can't take any money
back, then you're not gonna do תשובה. teshuvah. Now we got this
Twilight Zone that you're a גזלן gazlan and you steal it but
in order to encourage you to return it, you get rights to
the שבח shevach and you get to increase keep the שבח shevach
or portion of the שבח. shevach. And now we're gonna explore how
far do those rights go. So let's take a look. בעי רבא,
Ba'i Rava, so let's take a
look. And now the נגזל nigzal comes to get the animal back.
מה ששביח מכר מה ששביח הוריש. Ma she’shbiach machar ma she’shbiach horish.
So since he had rights to the שבח, shevach, so now the
person who bought it from him or the heir who received it
from him has rights to the שבח. shevach. So the נגזל nigzal
gets his sheep back, and the purchaser says, okay, but at least
pay me for the wool because the גזלן gazlan was allowed to
keep the wool, I'm allowed to keep the wool. Okay now, בעי
רבא, Ba'ei Rava, רבא Rava asks, השביח לוקח מהו? Hishbiach lokeach mahu?
Let's say the גזלן gazlan stole it, ראובן Reuven stole it and
then sold it to שמעון. Shimon. And now שמעון Shimon had it
increase in value, and then the נגזל nigzal comes. So שמעון Shimon
gets to keep the increase in value. Okay, מהו? mahu? בתר דבעיא
הדר פשטה, Batr de'ba'aya hadar pashata, after he raised the question he
concluded: מה מכר ראשון לשני כל זכות שבא
לידו. Ma machar rishon lishni kol zchut she'ba l'yado. Now there's a
classic phrase in the גמרא. Gemara. The first guy sold to the
second guy, he transferred any rights he had. So the same way
the גזלן gazlan has rights to keep the increase,
the לוקח lokeach has rights to keep the increase. בעי רבא, Ba'ei
Rava, so then רבא Rava asks, השביח עובד כוכבים מהו? Hishbiach oved
kochavim mahu? What about if it's a non-Jew who purchased it from
the... now we're going to have to see, is it a non-Jew
purchaser or is it a non-Jew גזלן? gazlan? But does the non-Jew
have rights to the שבח? shevach? Okay. אמר ליה רב אחאי מדפתי
לרבינא: Amar leh Rav Achai mi'Difti l'Ravina: תקנתא לעובדי כוכבים מיקו ונעביד?
Takanta l'ovdei kochavim meiku ve'nabdi? Are we going to come and make
a תקנתא takanta for the sake of the non-Jew? By the way,
the fact that he's finally using the word תקנתא takanta is helpful
because תוספות Tosafot until now has been explaining that this is all
תקנת השבים, Taknat Hashavim, right, a תקנתא takanah because why, to make
it easy for the גזלן gazlan to do תשובה. teshuvah. The גמרא
Gemara has not said what the reason is that the גזלן gazlan
has rights to the שבח. shevach. So here by using the word
תקנתא takanta discussing the non-Jew case, it seems to indicate that that's
what's going on for the גזלן gazlan as well. It's one thing
for the גזלן gazlan to give him a תקנתא takanah to let
him keep the שבח, shevach, but we're going to do it for
the case of the non-Jew? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה
לא צריכא כגון דזבנה לישראל. Amar leh lo tzricha k'gon dezavna l'Yisrael.
Okay fine, it's that the non-Jew, presumably we're still speaking the non-Jew
stole and then he sold it to a ישראל. Yisrael. So now
the ישראל Yisrael is the purchaser from the non-Jew גזלן, gazlan, does
that ישראל Yisrael have rights to the שבח? shevach? It says: סוף
סוף הבא מחמת עובד כוכבים הרי הוא כעובד כוכבים. Sof sof aba
machmat oved kochavim harei hu k'oved kochavim. But so what, if when
a non-Jew is a גזלן gazlan we don't let him keep the
שבח, shevach, why should we let the ישראל Yisrael who bought it
from him keep the שבח? shevach? So the גמרא Gemara says: לא
צריכא כגון דגזל ישראל. Lo tzricha k'gon degazal Yisrael. Okay fine, there
are three people involved. A ישראל Yisrael stole it, ראובן Reuven stole
it, וזבנה לעכו"ם, ve'zavna l'Akum, and then he sold it to Christopher,
והשביח עובד כוכבים, ve'hishbiach oved kochavim, and then Christopher made it
worth more, והדר עובד כוכבים וזבנה לישראל, ve'hadar oved kochavim ve'zavna l'Yisrael,
then Christopher went and sold it to שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so when
ראובן Reuven had it he had rights to the שבח, shevach, if
he had sold it straight to שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon would have
had rights to the שבח, shevach, but it went through Christopher in
the middle. So what do we say? Okay, מאי? Mai? מי אמרינן
כיון דמעיקרא ישראל והדר ישראל, Mi amrinan keivan dem'ikar Yisrael vehadar Yisrael,
started with a ישראל Yisrael and ended with a ישראל, Yisrael, עבדו
רבנן תקנתא, avdu rabanan takanta, so the תקנתא takanah of rights to
the שבח shevach still remains and therefore continues to pass through the
non-Jew and goes to the ישראל Yisrael at the end and he
has rights to the שבח? shevach? או דילמא כיון דאיכא עובד כוכבים
באמצע לא עבדו רבנן תקנתא? O dilma keivan d'ika oved kochavim bemtza
lo avdu rabanan takanta? Since the non-Jew is in the middle they
didn't. תיקו, Teku, we don't know. Fine. בודא. Buda. אמר רב פפא:
Amar Rav Pappa: האי מן Hai man now we're going to switch
back.
He didn't give him rights to the שבח, shevach, he
still has to pay ארבעה וחמישה arba ve'chamisha though, I mean if
this is a case of, oh
no, this is גזלן gazlan not גנב, gannav, good try, yeah.
If in this printing they use the phrase עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim,
is that unusual rather than, you know, גוי? Goy? גוי? Goy?
Yeah. Well, it's not unusual, it's usual as a censored word, meaning
the original version probably what did they have in Steinsaltz, גוי? Goy?
The original word would have been גוי Goy or sometimes נכרי. Nochri.
עובד כוכבים Oved kochavim is the classic censored word of, you know,
when it, yeah.
Okay, help me understand this, in this whole thing we had this
before, this Rabbinic תקנתא takanta was not, was only for a which,
גזלן gazlan or גנב? gannav?
גזלן. gazlan. Would we have said the same by גנב? gannav? So
that's an interesting question, you know because I've been pointing out from
the beginning that there are some conversations that seem that they should
be the exact same, like what type of a שינוי קונה shinuy
koneh or not, although the תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid actually questions that
that maybe there are different rules about that. But something like this
actually it makes sense that there might be a difference, like whether
we make a תקנתא, takanah, you know because by the גנב gannav
דוקא davka there's all these fines and punishments, I mean that's the
irony, so like what's going to incentivize him? But maybe what will
incentivize him is to return it so he doesn't have to pay
the כפל kefel and the ארבעה וחמישה arba ve'chamisha because if he's
מודה בקנס הוא פטור. modeh biknas hu patur. So anyway, but since
the, or another way of saying it is the גנב gannav is
a צורת הרשע tzorat harasha on. So maybe, you know, for whatever
reason, maybe you're right, we make more תקנתא takanot for the גזלן
gazlan than the גנב gannav because we did not see these types
of תקנתא takanot for the גנב. gannav. So that's a very good
point, you know that Michael raises, all these weird תקנתא takanot of,
you know, don't accept it back, let him keep the שבח, shevach,
you know, could be that by גנב gannav either for whatever reason
we're harsher we don't want to make it or because of the
harshness of the fines there's more of an incentive for him to
do תשובה teshuvah anyway. It's a good question. Okay, of course we
should raise the question why don't we do the same for a
גזלן, gazlan, make harsh fines if he's caught and then give him
the way to get out of it by admitting to it. That
would be a lot more. more justice, you know, just then than
to give make it give him all these all these like rewards
for returning it.
What you're getting at is an איתותרא itutra of an איתותרא, itutra,
right? Right. It's even more of an איתותרא itutra of an איתותרא.
itutra.
Right. Just as the גמרא Gemara before said
why is a
גנב ganav and a גזלן... gazlan... why is it more מחמיר machmir
by a גנב? ganav? Yes, right. That's one of the ways, right,
that's one of the ways the גמרא Gemara explains why we're more
מחמיר machmir by a גנב ganav is because he's like a hypocrite,
he has more יראה yira for בני אדם bnei adam than from
whatever. Okay. So you're saying if the גזלן gazlan doesn't care about
בני אדם, bnei adam, he's not going to be scared about
fines, maybe. Okay. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, now we switch
back though to a normal שינוי shinui conversation, and when people learn
מרובה Meruba and learn שינוי shinui מרובה Meruba they usually learn this
passage here of רב פפא. Rav Papa. Let's take a look. אמר
רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: האי מאן דגזל דיקלא מחבריה, Hai man
de-gazal dikla me-chavrei, somebody stole a palm tree from his friend. Now
again, how do you steal a palm tree? I don't know, you
claimed it. The way you're going to steal it is by chopping
it down, okay, and right now it's sort of קרקע אינה נגזלת.
karka eina nigzelet. But what you're going to do now is וקטליה,
v-katlei, and then you chopped it down. אף על גב
דשדייה מארעא לארעא דידיה, Af al gav de-shadyei me-ara l-ara didey, he
fell it from his friend's field into his yard, into his field,
that's how he stole it by chopping it down and it landed
in his yard. Okay. לא קני, Lo kani, you're not קונה. konei.
Now מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? מעיקרא דיקלא מקרי והשתא
נמי דיקלא מקרי. Mei-ikara dikla mikrei v-hashta nami dikla mikrei. Even though
you did שינוי מעשה, shinui maaseh, it was a שינוי מעשה shinui
maaseh without an attendant שינוי השם. shinui hashem. It was originally called
a palm tree and now it's just called a chopped down palm
tree. And that's pretty radical, okay, because first of all, I mean
there's a couple of things that are crazy about this, we can't
explore all of them, but number one, we've just gone through all
of this discussion about like a שינוי, shinui, like is a cow
after it gives birth a different cow and is that a שינוי
קונה? shinui konei? It gets a little fatter, it gets a little
thinner, there we consider it, that was like לא בידיים, lo b-yadayim,
not even a שינוי השם, shinui hashem, it was a little bit
of a physical change. Here you've chopped down a palm tree all
of a sudden it's not a big enough שינוי shinui because we'll
still call it a chopped down palm tree. And they call it
wood. I understand. And anyway we would assume you would call it
a different name, but even so compared to earlier discussions this seems
a lot bigger and more radical. It's both בידיים b-yadayim and we
would think you call it a שינוי השם. shinui hashem. That's number
one, I don't have an answer to that. The other point is
is that it sounds like if it was a שינוי shinui you
would be קונה. konei. But this is an interesting example of גזילה
ושינוי באים כאחד. gezeila v-shinui ba'im k-echad. Normally we assume the order
is you steal it and then you do a שינוי. shinui. But
here while it's still not chopped down you can't, it's not נגזל,
nigzal, right? You have to be able to make it מטלטלין metaltelin
and the chopping of it down is the act of the גזילה
gezeila and the גמרא Gemara implies that if in that act you
did a שינוי shinui it would be the גזילה ושינוי באים כאחד
gezeila v-shinui ba'im k-echad and you would be קונה, konei, but it
was not a שינוי. shinui. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
Okay.
והשתא נמי... V-hashta nami... no you don't hear an opposing opinion. Okay.
והשתא נמי דיקלא מקרי. V-hashta nami dikla mikrei. דיקלא ועבדא גובי. Dikla
v-avdei guvei.
Now if you stole a palm tree or maybe a chopped down
palm tree and you turned them into logs, לא קני, lo kani,
you're not קונה. konei. השתא מיהת גובי דדיקלא מקרי, Hashta mei-at guvei
d-dikla mikrei, they're called palm logs. Now גובי... guvei...
it's
specifically to palm
trees. Maybe. Any other tree...
it sounds like... maybe you're right. Maybe that has something to do
with a palm tree, I don't know. By the way, are palm
trees the ones that grow, or no, that's banana trees, that grow
new every year? That's banana trees. Okay. Because if it would be
something that you would chop down and regrow new every year you
could imagine it wouldn't be seen as radical. Anyway, גובי ועבדינהו כשורי,
Guvei v-avdinhu kishurei, if you took logs and made them into beams,
finally קני. kani. Ah, now we're קונה. konei. Okay. Beams are totally
different. I mean it is true, like you look at the lumber
industry, you look out at the forest, you know, and they have
all these big felled trees and the logs, they're all still in
a somewhat of a natural state, right? Once they get converted into
beams, that's already something different. Okay.
כשורי, Kishurei, if somebody stole a beam, רב זביד... Rav Zevid... ועבדינהו
כשורי זוטרי, v-avdinhu kishurei zutrei, and made it into a small beam,
you took a two-by-four and you made it into two one-by-fours or
something, I don't know, okay, לא קני, lo kani, you're not קונה.
konei. That's just not enough of a שינוי. shinui. They're just different
beams, they're not fundamentally different.
עבדינהו קצוציתא, Avdinhu kitzutzita, if however you made it into a...
no, קצוציתא kitzutzita is a different type of a thing, it's like,
I don't know, boards. Boards. Okay, like planks. So that is a
two-by-four as opposed to a beam, I guess this is more much
more, you know, substantial.
Two-by-four is... no, but two-by-fours are thin, right? Planks, like as opposed
to like a beam which is more like three-dimensionally fully three-dimensional. Okay.
דקני, de-kani, then קני, kani, that is different. אמר רבא: Amar Rava:
האי מאן דגזל לולבא ועבדיה הוצי, Hai man de-gazal lulava v-avdei hutzi,
if somebody stole a לולב lulav and turned it into like a
broom, basically you took... you plucked out all of the leaves and
you bound it back against the stem and now it's like a
broom. What? That's very significant. Yeah, I guess so. Okay. קני, Kani,
that's already a קנין. kinyan. דמעיקרא לולבא מקרי והשתא הוצי, de-mei-ikara lulava
mikrei v-hashta nami hutzi, before it was a לולב lulav and now
it's a broom. הוצי ועבדינהו חופיא. Hutzi v-avdinhu chofya. Now חופיא... chofya...
I'm sorry, חופיא chofya is the broom. I don't know what the
הוצי hutzi was. But
the... the חופיא chofya is...
Okay, the חופיא chufya was like the broom, except apparently what you
did is you split the leaves into two. So it wasn't just
that you detached the leaves and bound them back up, but each
of the leaves you sort of split. In that case, קני, kani,
how do they translate the difference between חופיא chufya and...
right, he says the first one is leaves that
he tore the leaves off
the לולב lulav
branch, and now he has to bind them back up to it
to make it into a
broom.
Alright, whatever, anyway fine. So you're pulling the leaves off and then
you're binding it back and then you're splitting the leaves in half.
קני, kani, מעיקרא הוצי והשתא חופיא, me'ikara hutzei vehashta chufya, before it
was like leaves, now it's a broom.
Here's an explanation. It says that when making a broom, the double
leaves are split along their folds and tied together to form a
broom.
Okay, that's what I said, right, you split the leaves into two.
Okay, irreversible change. Got it. חופיא ועבדינהו שרשורא, chufya ve'avdineihu sharshura, now
if you took the if you took the leaves and you wove
them into some type of a like of a rope, then לא
קני, lo kani, you're not קונה. koneh. Why? מאי טעמא דהדר סתרה
לה? mai ta'ama dehadar satrah leh? This is the idea that even
if it's a radical change, if it could be undone and you
could undo the rope and get you back into the into the
leaves, then that's not then that's חוזר לברייתו chozer livriyato והוי חופיא,
vehavei chufya, make it back into this broom. Okay, בעי רב פפא.
ba'ei Rav Pappa. Rav Pappa asks, now this is going to be
strange. נחלקה התיומת מהו? nechelka ha-tiyomet mahu? Right, sounds like it's going
to
sound like it. What happens if the tip is cut off? תא
שמע דאמר רב מתנה אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי נטלה התיומת, ta
shema de'amar Rav Mattanah amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi nitlah ha-tiyomet, no,
if the tip tip is split. So Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi says
נטלה התיומת פסול. nitlah ha-tiyomet pasul. If it's cut off, it's a
פסול לולב. pasul lulav. So מאי לאו הוא הדין לנחלקה, mai lav
hu hadin lenechelka, shouldn't we say the same would be if it
split? So since it would be a פסול לולב, pasul lulav, it's
a שינוי shinuy and you're קונה. koneh. Now I want to say,
is this happening on סוכות? Succos? Is it a כשר לולב kasher
lulav that you made פסול? pasul? Then I would get that it's
a שינוי. shinuy. But maybe it's not happening on סוכות, Succos, like
you know, I mean, you know. So Rashi says וכיון דעבד בה
פסולא לענין מצוה לענין מקנה נמי שינוי הוי וקני. vekeivan de'avad bah
pesula le'inyan mitzvah le'inyan miknah nami shinuy havei vekani. Since it's פסול
pasul for הלכות לולב, hilchos lulav, it's a שינוי. shinuy. To me
that only makes sense if it's happening on סוכות. Succos. Okay. Anyway,
so he says presumably split is the same as cut off. לא
נטלה שאני. lo nitlah shani. No, cut off is different. דחסר ליה,
dechasar leh, it's lacking. איכא דאמרי תא שמע דאמר רב מתנה אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי נחלקה התיומת נעשית כמי שנטלה ופסול. ika de'amri
ta shema de'amar Rav Mattanah amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi nechelka ha-tiyomet
na'aseit kemi shenitlah u-pasul. If it's split, it's like it's cut off
and it's פסול. pasul. And therefore שמע מינה, shema mina, that's a
good proof, and since it's פסול, pasul, presumably you're קונה. koneh.
That's a perfectly good broom.
I understand. אמר רב פפא האי מאן דגזל עפרא מחבריה ועבדיה לבינתא.
amar Rav Pappa hai man de-gazal afra me-chavreih ve'avdeih levinta. If somebody
stole dust, dirt, from the friend, and
you know, basically made it into a brick, okay, so you used
it and you added whatever you needed to turn it into a
brick, לא קני, lo kani, you're not קונה. koneh. That seems a
pretty radical change. מאי טעמא דהדר משוי ליה עפרא? mai ta'ama dehadar
mashvei leh afra? You can crush it and make it back into
dust. So this is again the principle of שינוי החוזר לברייתו, shinuy
hachozer livriyato, even if it will it went underwent a radical change
and it would have to go under a radical change to get
back, since eventually it could get back, it's considered חוזר לברייתו. chozer
livriyato.
But I still have the option, right, of just giving him other
dirt?
No, he still owns it. Not the תקנת השבים taknat hashavim and
all that? Oh, so he might have to pay for the difference.
We're back to the case about like the the increased wool. Okay,
that's a good point, he might have to pay for the difference.
לבינתא ועבדיה עפרא, levinta ve'avdeih afra, let's say you stole a brick
and you turned it into dust, קני, kani, you're קונה. koneh. מהו
דתימא דילמא הדר ועביד ליה לבינתא? mahu deteima dilma hadar ve'avid leh
levinta? Oh no, it's חוזר לברייתו, chozer livriyato, I can remold it
back into a brick. No, האי לבינתא אחריתי היא. hai levinta achriti
hi. That's a new brick, it's not the same brick. פנים חדשות
באו לכאן, panim chadashos bau lechan, and that's considered something new. So
the dust is considered the same dust, okay, but a brick you
when you make something new, it's it's a similar item to the
one you stole, okay, but it's not the same item that you
stole.
You understand about that?
But you can't make a brick with just dust, you're putting more
than dust in it, the water...
yeah, I was wondering about that too. Right, like why is it
exactly the same? But I guess it's it has the additives, but
it contains the same, it is the same dust plus other stuff.
Okay, anyway, so I don't know. ואמר רב פפא האי מאן דגזל
נסכא מחבריה ועבדיה זוזי. ve'amar Rav Pappa hai man de-gazal naska me-chavreih
ve'avdeih zuzei. If you stole a piece of metal from your friend,
and you made it into a coin, לא קני, lo kani, you're
not קונה. koneh. Now here by the way, Jenna, presumably you could
do this just by minting it without adding anything. מאי טעמא דהדר
עביד להו נסכא? mai ta'ama dehadar avid lehu naska?
Because then you could just, you know, flatten it and turn it
back into into metal, into a non-coin form. זוזי ועבדינהו נסכא, zuzei
ve'avdineihu naska, however, if you stole coins and you melted them down
into metal, קני, kani, then you are קונה. koneh. מהו דתימא הדר
עביד להו זוזי? mahu deteima hadar avid lehu zuzei?
Oh, why? I can turn it back into coins. No, פנים חדשות
באו לכאן, panim chadashos bau lechan, that would be a new coin.
שחימי ועבדינהו חרתי, shichimei ve'avdineihu charatei,
if you stole blackened coins and you polished them and made them
new, לא קני, lo kani, you're not קונה. koneh. Because you know,
that's חוזר לברייתו. chozer livriyato. First of all, to what degree is
that a שינוי השם shinuy hashem anyway? Is it called something new?
It's just maybe just called something polished. But anyway, you leave it
around long enough it'll get black again. חרתי ועבדינהו שחימי, charatei ve'avdineihu
shichimei, if you stole new ones and you made them blackened ones,
קני, kani, you're קונה. koneh. Now that's weird, why? Just
polished... the whatever it is, the rust or what makes coins black?
Silver oxidizing becomes black.
Okay, so the silver oxidizing or whatever, you just remove that stuff,
so you can't say פנים חדשות באו לכאן Panim chadashot ba'u l'chan
because it's not, you're just revealing the old coin. But the Gemara
says no, because it's not fully חוזר לבריאתו. chozer l'vriato. Some of
the blackness still remains. You're never going to fully polish it again.
Is that true? When I polish my silver, it really looks like
you totally get it back to new state.
It looks, but you've actually lost a tiny bit of the silver
each time that you polish it.
Oh, really? It's good to have you in Shiur, Charlie. Okay, let's
go.
But let me skip back to the first case. Right?
No, yeah, quickly because I want to
get to the next case. Well, we do get, I do get
compensated for the increase, but if I, let's say, put it in
my house, then I...
Yeah, then it'd be like כשעת הגזילה. k'sha'at hag'zeilah. זה הכלל כל
הגזלנין משלמין כשעת הגזילה. Zeh haklal kol hagazlanin m'shalmin k'sha'at hag'zeilah. Everybody
pays based on the value what it was when you stole it.
לאתויי מאי? L'atuyei mai? What does this זה הכלל zeh haklal come
to include? לאתויי הא דאמר רב אילא, L'atuyei ha d'amar Rav Ila,
and this was mentioned yesterday. גנב טלה ונעשה איל עגל ונעשה שור.
Ganav taleh v'na'aseh ayil egel v'na'aseh shor. If you stole a sheep
and it became a ram, a calf and it became an ox,
נעשה שינוי בידו וקנאו. Na'aseh shinui b'yado u'kna'o. Now it's a שינוי
shinui and you own it. טבח ומכר שלו הוא טובח ושלו הוא
מוכר. Tavach u'machar shelo hu tovach u'shelo hu mocher. And this is
from a גניבה gneivah case. So if you slaughter and sell it,
it's yours, you don't pay four and five. Now if you might
remember, there was that great line in the Gemara in מרובה Meruba
wherever it said back to him, you know, רחמנא ליצלן מדעתא דידך.
Rachmana litzlan mida'ata didach. Like what a crazy idea, God save us
from such opinions. And then he said back, אדרבה רחמנא ליצלן מדעתא
דידך. Adaraba Rachmana litzlan mida'ata didach. God save us from your opinion.
It was like a great exchange. Anyway, here the Gemara quotes it
without any dispute. Okay? And on the one hand, it's a שינוי
השם shinui hashem without any שינוי מעשה. shinui ma'aseh. It's a physical
difference, but not a physical difference that you imposed on it, that
happened by itself. Okay? And here it is calling it a שינוי.
shinui. So chopping down a palm tree and turning it into logs,
that's not a שינוי. shinui. You know, this here is a שינוי,
shinui, okay. But anyway, in this case because you now own it,
you just pay the original value, and this is נעשה שינוי בידו
וקנאו. na'aseh shinui b'yado u'kna'o. Okay. אמר ההוא גברא דגזל פדנא דתורי
מחבריה. Amar hahu gavra d'gazal padna d'torei m'chavrei. Somebody stole a pair
of oxen from his friend. אזל וכרב בהו כרבא. Azal v'charav behu
karva.
He went and he plowed, you know, plowing, he plowed his field
with it. זרע בהו זרעא. Zara behu zara. And then he planted
his land, so he stole some cows, used them to plow and
to, you know, plant his field. לסוף אהדרינהו למריה. L'sof ahadrinhu l'marei.
And then he said thank you very much, I'm going to return
the גזילה, g'zeilah, okay, and I don't have to pay you anything.
So אתא לקמיה דרב נחמן. Ata l'kamei d'Rav Nachman. The owner came
to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Now this was not that the גזילה
g'zeilah increased, this was used the גזילה g'zeilah to make his land
increase.
אמר ליה זיל שום שבחא דאשבח. Amar lei zil shum shivcha d'ashbach.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman said,
go figure out how much the land increased and have the גזלן
gazlan pay the owner for the increase of the land. This is
like the exact opposite of what we've seen before. Before I increase
your גזילה g'zeilah and you have to reimburse me. Here I use
your cows to increase my land and I have to reimburse you
for how my land increased. So why? I understand. So let's take
a look. אמר ליה רבא. Amar lei Rava. So רבא Rava the
first thing רבא Rava said is: even if that were true, that
you have to reimburse the owner for what you benefited, תורי אשבח
ארעא לא אשבח? Torei ashbach ara lo ashbach? The cows made the
increase the value and the land didn't increase the value? Meaning the
reason the land is worth more is not all based, if the
land is now worth a hundred dollars more, it's not that the
cows contributed a hundred dollars worth of effort, right? The cow might
have contributed a portion of what it was but the land itself
was because it led to its increase in value. אמר מי קאמינא
נשומה כולה? Amar mi kamina n'shumei kulei? I didn't say pay for,
I didn't mean to say you'd pay the full amount. אלא פלגא
קאמינא Ela palga kamina and pay for half of the increase, pay
back to the owner. אמר ליה סוף סוף גזילה
היא. Amar lei sof sof g'zeilah hi. I don't understand this, it's
a גזילה g'zeilah case. וקא הדרא בעינה V'ka hadra b'einah and the
גזילה g'zeilah is returning in its current, in its original form. דתנן
כל הגזלנין משלמין כשעת הגזילה. D'tnan kol hagazlanin m'shalmin k'sha'at hag'zeilah. You
pay based on the way it was and we've already looked at
what that means is, if anything, the owner has to pay you
if the גזילה g'zeilah increases. So now you use the גזילה g'zeilah
to increase land, you're going to have to give him back more
than you took? No, you only give the guy back the amount
that you took, why are you going to have to give him
back the increase in the land? אמר ליה לאו אמינא לך כי
יתיבנא בדינא לא תימא לי מידי? Amar lei lav amina lach ki
yativna b'dina lo teima li midi? He said to him, haven't I
told you,
when I'm sitting in דין, din, don't talk to me? Okay, meaning
presumably it means don't second guess me. It could mean don't distract
me, but it sounds like don't second guess me. דאמר הונא חבראי,
D'amar Huna chavrai, Huna our friend, my colleague has said, עלי alai
regarding me, okay this is רב נחמן Rav Nachman talking, אנא ושבור
מלכא ana u'Shvor Malka that I, רב נחמן Rav Nachman and שבור
מלכא Shvor Malka who was like the you know,
who is a name for שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel was called שבור
מלכא, Shvor Malka, so אחי בדינא. achi b'dina. We, I mean, שבור
מלכא Shvor Malka was the name of like the Persian head of
government or whatever, but שמואל Shmuel was very buddy-buddy with him, anyway
so it was a way of referring to שמואל. Shmuel. We're like
colleagues in דין. din. Meaning we are like, we know what we're
doing when it comes to cases of דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. Okay?
Don't second guess me. האי אינש גזלנא עתיקא הוא, hai inish gazlana
atika hu, this guy was an old גזלן, gazlan, was a habitual
גזלן, gazlan, ובעינא דאיקנסיה, uve'ina de'iknesay, exactly opposite what we were saying,
and he needs to be fined. So technically you're right, he just
should give it back and he shouldn't have to give back the
value, the increase that he received, but you know, he needs some
extra slap on the hand, he needs some extra punishment, so him
I'm going to make it. So again, it's exactly opposite, all these
things as we go easy on the גזלן, gazlan, let them keep
the stuff to increase him, and when he's a habitual גזלן gazlan
we go even easier on him, and here we find that no,
sometimes actually a little common sense has to kick in and we
have to go in the opposite direction. Yes, Charlie?
What has been missing from this סוגיא sugya is הפקר בית דין
הפקר, hefker beit din hefker, which gives the, gives the בית דין
beit din the power to
engage—well, that's presumably something of what was operating in this last case—that's
what
I think, but it's not mentioned.
Yeah, exactly.